# Francesco Scala

#### PHD STUDENT IN QUANTUM MACHINE LEARNING

Pavia, Italy

□ (+39) 3406416189 | strancesco.scala01@ateneopv.it | # Work page: fisica.unipv.it/personale/Persona.php?ID=591 |
# Personal page: fran-scala.github.io/ | □ fran-scala | □ fran-scala



# Summary\_

I'm an eager third-year PhD student in Quantum Machine Learning (QML) at University of Pavia, focusing on both classical and quantum machine learning. I bring strong foundations in state-of-the-art theoretical aspects of QML as well as proficiency in numerical simulations of quantum computing systems and QML algorithms. Thanks to my collegiate and representative of PhD students experience, I am used to interdisciplinary and challenging environments. Apart from the academic side, I'm an outgoing and active person enjoying sports, gardening and travelling.

# Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

#### **FULL-TIME**

Mar - May 2024 Reserach intern IBM Research

Zurich - Switzerland

Research internship focused on Quantum Machine Learning. My supervisors are Dr. Ivano Tavernelli and Dr. Francesco Tacchino, I closely work also with Dr. Christa Zoufal.

2021 - present

PhD in Quantum Machine Learning Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia – Italy

My research deals with **QML algorithms**, with special focus on **overparametrization** and **regularization** properties of **Quantum Neural Networks**. Part of my studies are also devoted to simulations of quantum computing platforms. My supervisor is Prof. **Dario Gerace**.

#### PART-TIME

Oct 2022-present Teaching assistant Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia - Italy

• Lectures on General Physics at the degree program in Chemistry and Pharmaceutical Technologies

Jul - Dec 2022

Intern QUANTUM COMPUTING LAB - CINECA

Casalecchio di Reno (BO) - Italy

• Benchmarking of **HPC infrastructures** for quantum computing and **QML applications** (Python)

#### Education

2019 - 2021 Master degree in Physics of Quantum Technologies Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia – Italy

Graduation date: 23-09-2021, Thesis: "Witnessing Entanglement by Quantum Neural Networks".

2016 - 2019

Oct 2023

Jun 2023

Bachelor degree in Physics Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia – Italy

Graduation date: 24-09-2019, Thesis: "Machine learning techniques applied to the quantum many-body problem".

# Contributions: conferences, schools \_\_\_\_\_

Nov 2023 Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning (QTML) 2023 CERN

Geneve - Switzerland

Talk: A General Approach to Dropout in Quantum Neural Networks

Quantum Computing and Simulation Workshop ISTITUTO VENETO

Venezia - Italy

**Poster**: A General Approach to Dropout in Quantum Neural Networks

Aug 2023 Superconducting Qubits and Algorithms (SQA) Conference IQM QUANTUM COMPUTERS

Munich - Germany

Lecce - Italy

**Poster**: Symmetrizing Quantum Machine Learning for Quantum Field Theory

International Conference on Optics of Excitons in Confined Systems Università del Salento

Talk: Quantum computing platform with polariton integrated circuits

Nov 2022	Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning (QTML) 2022 UNIVERSITY FEDERICO II	Napoli - Italy
	Poster: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	
Ago - Sept 2022	VCQ & AppQlinfo SummerSchool 2022 UNIVERSITÄT WIEN	Wien - Austria
	Student Talk: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	
Jul 2022	World Congress On Computational Intelligence 2022 IEEE	Padova – Italy
	<b>Talk</b> : Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	
Jun 2022	Quantum Computing Hard- and Software Summer School 2022 EPFL, ETH ZÜRICH	Lausanne - Switzerland
	Poster: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	

## **Extracurricular Activities**

Feb 2024 2nd Place QHACK 2024 - XANADU Online • Topic: Spectral Gap estimation • Spectral Gap Superposition States [paper] [Github] **Technical-scientific Committee Member** BeQUANTUM Apr 2023 - present Online - Italy • Production of technical posts. General posts review. May 2023 1st Place ETH QUANTUM HACKATHON 2023 - IQM CHALLENGE Zurich - Switzerland • Topic: Exploiting symmetries in Quantum Machine Learning • Tasks: TicTacToe (given), Schwinger model (our proposal) [Github] Apr 2022 - Jul 2022 Mentee QUANTUM OPEN SOURCE FOUNDATION (QOSF) Online • Implementation of Krylov module within tequila Python package [Github] • Mentor: Prof. Jakob Kottmann Phd Student representative Università degli Studi di Pavia Pavia - Italy 2nd Place MIT IQUHACK 2022 - MICRSOFT/IONQ DIVISION Online

# Skills\_

- Programming: Python, C++(basic)
- Quantum programming: Pennylane (in combination with JAX), Qiskit, tequila, AWS Braket
- Soft skills: predisposition to interpersonal relationships, teamwork, quick learner, proactive, time management

# **Languages .**

Italian: Native English: Level C1 French: Level A1

• Topic: Quantum game with educational purposes

• Blackjack-inspired quantum game named QuHackJack [Github]

### Publications

F. Scala et al.		arXiv:2402.17668 Spectral Gap Superposition States	2024 (Preprint)
F. Scala et al.		Adv. Quantum Tech. 2300220 A GENERAL APPROACH TO DROPOUT IN QUANTUM NEURAL NETWORKS	2023
F. Scala et al.		arXiv:2306.05072 DETERMINISTIC ENTANGLING GATES WITH NONLINEAR QUANTUM PHOTONIC INTERFEROMETER	2023 (In review)
J. Kottmann, F. Scala	I	arXiv:2302.10660 COMPACT EFFECTIVE BASIS GENERATION: INSIGHTS FROM INTERPRETABLE CIRCUIT DESIGN	2023 (Acc. by JCTC)
F. Scala et al.		IEEE - IJCNN 2022 Proceedings Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	2022